Michael Penhallegon

Seattle, WA 98144 / (425) 243-9426 / mike@hematite.tech

Summary:

A Data Engineer with a focus in data wrangling/transformation, building data pipelines and ETL processes in devops environments. Has a diverse set of skills from application development and data analytics. Has utilized mixtures of skill-sets to develop projects improving the data utilization and access of data to answer research and business questions. Love new challenges and investigating applications of data science and data processing in new contexts.

- 7-years of experience with Python and advanced knowledge of R, Scala, Java and SQL
- Developed skills in understand and designing solution to wrangle and process fragmented data; gaining greater insight using exploratory and descriptive statistical technique.
- Collaborative leadership demonstrating an ability to connect business owners with data solutions
- Complimentary Devops skill sets utilizing AWS Kinesis, EC2, S3, Apache Airflow, Kafka and Docker

Professional Experience:

Bristol-Myers Squibb

Associate Data Scientist

Seattle, WA

August 2018-Present

Collaborated with translational science researchers and clinicians on utilizing technology to deliver answers to

- Transitioned and promoted from Research Associate to Associate Data Scientist
- Designed, tested and implemented projects in Python, R and Scala to process, format and ingest clinical trial data into data warehouses and data stores, like Labkey and AWS Redshift
- Developed and released internally 2 R Packages utilized to process and upload data to a data warehouse.
- Utilized SQL to aggregate and combine data; connect and corelate disparate datasets and maintain data quality. Allowing more holistic use of translational medicine research metrics to investigate research questions

Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center

research questions in clinical trials

Seattle, WA

Research Intern

June 2017-June 2018

- Placed in the HIV Vaccine Trial Network Core Lab. Inclusive of two internship terms (Summer 2017 & Spring 2018) with complimentary work between terms.
- Completed thorough literature review and prepared results for publication in an academic journal.
- Contributed to a qualitative research project investigating HIV/AIDS stigma among HIV+ and HIV- men
- Developed and published an R package, to linearly interpolate Census-data to generate heath metric values.

The Evergreen State College

Olympia, WA

Math Tutor

September 2017-June 2018

- Working in the college math center tutoring algebra, calculus and computer science subjects
- Tutored mathematics up to differential calculus, discrete mathematics, programming and digital logic
- · Learned and used equity-minded pedagogy to tutor and engage students in using quantitative skill sets

The Evergreen State College

Olympia, WA

Outreach and Retention Advisor

June 2016-June 2018

- Advised and mentored first-generation/low-income students in navigating college and achieving success through a federal grant sponsored Trio program.
- Assisted linking college administration to students through development of job descriptions, running candidate student forums and recruitment of students to college committees

Stonewall Youth, Olympia, WA

Olympia, WA

Programming Coordinator

October 2015-June 2016

- Developed programming for at-risk LGBTQ youth; Helped maintain drop-in hours for participants
- Developed backup plan; edited and maintained WordPress site including backup and software updates
- Utilized Python and R to clean and restore both participant and donor data. Normalized data from legacy systems.

Peninsula College

Port Angeles, WA

Office Assistant, Longhouse Diversity Services

February 2014-June 2014

- Coordinated event management for two large campus-wide events
- Maintained, updated and transitioned tribal contact database from Microsoft Excel to Access

Education:

The Evergreen State College

September 2015-June 2018

Bachelor of Art, emphasis in Computer Science and Public Health Studies

Peninsula College

January 2013-June-2015

Associate of Art, Direct Transfer Agreement/General Studies

Volunteer Experience:

King-Snohomish-Island Counties Ryan White Grant Review Committee, Member, October 2018-December 2018

AIDS Memorial Pathway Project, Committee Volunteer, August 2018-Present

The Evergreen State College Provost Search Committee, Member, September 2016-January 2017

Nomenus, Active Member, June 2009-Present

Skills:

General: 65 wpm, interpersonal skills, customer service, and consensus decision-making. **Computing:** Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access, Outlook), Tableau, Tibco Spotfire, Mac, Windows, and Linux desktop environments. **Programming and Software Development:** Python, R, Java, Scala, git, Jira, HTML/CSS, JQuery, PostgreSQL, MariaDB, test-driven development (TDD). **Cloud Computing Technolgies:**

Professional Memberships

American Public Health Association, 2017-present, Member